Guide to the Witter Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Witter family papers
1752-1852
1781-1852
MS 1075
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
The papers consist of legal papers, medical accounts, religious writings, and other papers relating to Avery Downer, Jacob Witter, and their relations, including Jonah and John Witter.
Witter family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Henry W. Beckwith, 1940 and 1943, and Mrs. John H. Quinlan, 1948.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Witter Family Papers consist of miscellaneous items related to Avery Downer (1762-1854) of Preston, Conn., Jacob Witter (1737-1798) of Norwich, Conn., and several of their relations. The papers of Avery Downer have to do with his career as a physician, including his service in the Revolution. The papers of Jacob Witter are legal documents and religious writings. Jacob Witter's grandnephew, John Witter (1785-1858; Y. 1812) is represented by a play, "The Lounger," said to have been produced unofficially around the time of his graduation. The connection between the two lines is that Lucas Witter, one of Jacob's nephews married Avery Downer's second daughter, Emily. For more genealogical information see The Witter Genealogy and The Downers of America.
Biographical / Historical
John Witter, the eldest son and second child of Jonah Witter, of Brooklyn, then part of Pomfret, Connecticut, and grandson of Nathan and Keziah (Branch) Witter, of Brooklyn, was born in Brooklyn on April 28, 1785. His mother was Eunice Cady, of Brooklyn. The Rev. Thomas Williams (Yale 1800) was a first cousin, and Professor John H. Hewitt (Yale 1859) is a nephew. In the year of his birth his parents removed to Preston, and after having taught for a few terms he was prepared for College by John Adams (Yale 1795) in Bacon Academy, Colchester.
For the three years next after graduation he taught in the Hopkins Grammar School in Hartford. He then returned to Yale as Tutor, declining the offer of a post in the Academy where he was educated. In March, 1816, he united with the College Church on profession of his faith.
In the fall of 1817, he returned to Bacon Academy, and on April 30, 1819, he was married to Eliza Loomis, eldest child of Asa and Sophia (Loomis) Bulkeley, of Colchester.
After a few years he became principal of the Academy in Plainfield; and after retiring from that position his residence continued in the town, where he was occupied with the cultivation of his farm and occasional teaching until his death on December 30, 1858, in his 74th year.
He maintained a good reputation as a scholar and as an instructor, and was esteemed for his high character. He was for years a deacon in the Congregational Church in Plainfield.
After the death of his first wife, he married Olive Smith, of Plainfield.
By his first marriage he had three daughters and two sons. One son and one daughter died in infancy.
(Taken from F. B. Dexter, Biographical Sketches of Yale College, Class of 1812, pp. 505-506).
Families; Groton Heights, Battle of, Conn., 1781; Medicine, Military; Medicine; Religious tolerance; Connecticut -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783; New London (Conn.) -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783 -- Campaigns; Physicians; Downer, Avery, 1762-; Witter, Jacob, 1737-1798; Witter family
- Inventory
  - Avery Downer (1762-1854)
    - Memorandum, "An Uncommon Occurrence," relating to his certification by a committee of the New London County medical association, 1784 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Medical account book containing a narrative of the Battle of Groton Heights, 1847-1852, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Revolutionary Reminiscence" to the editor of the New London Daily Star, 1849 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "Names of Persons wounded in Groton [Fort?] on the 6th of September 1781 and attended on by Avery Downer...", undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Note on the medical effects of music and dancing, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Mary Ann Downer (1802-1880): commonplace books, 1830, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - John Labastide: valentine, 1784 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Salmon Treat: deed to Asher Rossiter for land in Preston, Connecticut, 1752 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Jacob Witter (1737-1798)
    - Papers relating to Jonah Witter's activities as conservator of his estate, 1785-1799 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "A Short Treatise on the Duty and Necessity of Universal Christian Fellowship and the Obsurdity [sic] and Wickedness of Christians Refusing Fellowship with Those of other Denominations", undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "Meditations on Various Religious Subjects", undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - John Witter (1785-1858): colloquy, "The Lounger", 1812 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Samuel W. Wood: ALS to his (father-in-law?), Jonah Witter, 1833 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Photograph, "Jacob Witter house, Bean Hill, Connecticut/The Witter & Hyde [Tavern?]", undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Raw silk fiber and cocoon, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)